A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, AIA-IBEC, Series B FA339
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, AIA-IBEC, Series B
1945-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
FA339
40 document box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 B
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents note
This series includes 16 cubic feet of Nelson A. Rockefeller's personal copies of correspondence, reports, and publications reflecting his interest in the development and management of two private international development agencies: the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) and the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC).
The AIA was established in July 1946 by Nelson Rockefeller as a nonprofit philanthropic organization to help underdeveloped countries combat poverty, disease, and illiteracy by disseminating technical and managerial expertise and equipment. The AIA worked closely with local governments and other established organizations to develop programs that could eventually be supported and managed locally. The AIA was active primarily in rural rehabilitation and agricultural development. It developed farm and extension services to provide training in agriculture (helping farmers improve their dairy herds and diversify crops) and home economics. To help farmers establish credit and secure loans from local banks, the AIA established rural credit and assistance associations such as ACAR (Associacao de Credito e Assistencia Rural) and ABCAR (Associacao Brasileira de Credito e Assistencia Rural). AIA was also active in agricultural research and nutritional education and in improving rural roads, communications, and primary education. While this series primarily documents operations in Venezuela and Brazil, where the agency was most active, there is also documentation of AIA operations in Peru, Panama, Puerto Rico, and India.
IBEC was established in January 1947 for the same general purposes as AIA, but it was operated as a for-profit business. It focused on developing the "basic economies" of underdeveloped countries and thus encouraged others in those countries to establish competitive businesses. By 1971 IBEC had established almost 200 separate companies in 33 countries. These businesses were involved in supermarkets, agricultural services, milk processing and distribution, mutual funds, middle-income housing, poultry breeding, and manufacturing. In Venezuela, IBEC operated through a subsidiary, the Venezuelan Basic Economy Corporation (VBEC). Between 1947 and 1955, VBEC established companies in farming (PACA), fishing (PESCA), and wholesale (CADA), as well as a milk company (INLACA). In Brazil, IBEC provided specialized services to farmers to upgrade production through a hybrid seed company (SASA), a hog production company (SAFAP), a helicopter crop dusting company (HELICO), and a mechanized agricultural services company designed to clear and cultivate virgin land (EMA). IBEC also developed a method of producing low-cost poured concrete homes in Puerto Rico, Chile, Peru, Mexico, Iraq, and Iran. In the process IBEC helped to develop and market the Cinva Ram press, a pioneering tool for making bricks. Another subsidiary, V. D. Anderson, sold and installed oil extraction, continuous rendering, and synthetic rubber machinery throughout the world. The poultry endeavors of IBEC were merged with a U.S. poultry breeding company, Arbor Acres Farm, Inc., to introduce breeding plants into 15 developing countries. In Thailand IBEC had a coconut fiber plant and a cotton and silk textile and clothing firm making use of the unique designs of the Thai culture.
Other major topics include ANCAR (The Northeastern Association of Credit and Rural Assistance); highway construction in Brazil; iron ore and sulfite projects in Brazil; General Coffee Company; H.P. Hood & Sons; AIA work in India; IBEC study of Italy and Ireland; IBEC Research Institute reports on corn, coffee, and cereal in Brazil, Venezuela, and Ecuador; IBEC Technical Services airport survey; IBEC and Avila oil investments in Texas; IBEC Housing Corporation; AIA finances and contributions; Juancito Salud comic books; IBEC Economic Development Corporation; IBEC Research Institute; IBEC supermarkets; and IBEC Investing Corporation.
The development of these projects and proposals for others are documented in this series. The material includes Nelson Rockefeller's original handwritten notes outlining the purpose, objectives, and structure of what would later become AIA and IBEC and his notes on his visits with President Romulo Betancourt of Venezuela in 1947, as well as his handwritten comments on various memos, reports, and letters.
The bulk of the material covers the period from the establishment of the two agencies to 1958, when Nelson Rockefeller resigned his presidencies to assume his new duties as governor of New York. There are a few documents dated as late as 1971.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
Related Materials
For related materials at RAC see:
FA079 American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) records
FA084 International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) records
New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Philanthropy -- United States; Economic policy; Economics; Education; National security -- United States; Business enterprises, Foreign; Civic improvement; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Civics; Developing countries; Art, Primitive; Arts; Brazil; Business; Philanthropy; United States; State governments -- United States; Venezuela; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Social problems -- Latin America; Public health -- Latin America; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Government agencies; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Agriculture -- Latin America; Agriculture; Education -- Latin America; Federal government -- United States; International relations -- United States; Latin America; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; International economic relations; International relations; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); United Nations; United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services; International Basic Economy Corporation; United States. Office of Inter-American Affairs; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); American International Association for Economic and Social Development; United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs; United States. Dept. of State. Bureau of Western Hemisphere Affairs; United States. President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization; Hinman, George
- AIA - Bolivar Foundation, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Proposed predecessor of AIA. Was to be a high governmental operation to improve living standards and industry in LAtin America. Kadow preliminary proposals on program and staff. Change of name to AIA in Feb. 1946. Beginnings of IBEC (International Basic Economy Corporation). Correspondents include NAR, F. P. Corrigan, Eugene Holman, K.J. Kadow.
- AIA - General, 1946-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Certificate of Incorporation. Cooperation in Venezuela documents. Report on early projects. NAR's comments on purpose of AIA. Organization of International Development Services, Inc. Project proposals. Changes in Program. Oil company participation. Status reports. Louise A. Boyer. Correspondents include NAR, John E. Lockwood, W. K. Harrison, John Camp.
- AIA - Alton, W. H., 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Report on 1947 inspection trip of AIA in Venezuela and Brazil. Correspondents include NAR, W. H. Alton.
- AIA - ANCAR (Northeastern Association of Credit and Rural Assistance) - Brazil, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Budget, 1956 report on progress. Correspondents include Walter Crawford.
- AIA - Anderson, V. D. Co., 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Purchase of company by IBEC (International Basic Economy Corporation). Equipment claim by Venezuelan firm. Correspondents include NAR, Francis A. Jamieson.
- AIA - Barbosa, T. Q., 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Brazilian representative. Conditions in Brazil. Changes in N.Y. office. Changing program. NAR comments on changing management teams. Both AIA and IBEC activities. Correspondents include NAR, T. Q. Barbosa.
- AIA - Brazil, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Personnel activity reports, progress. Brazilian conditions. Spread of programs in Brazil. Purcell - Aldrich correspondence investments in Brazil. IBEC related items. Correspondents include NAR, John Camp, Harry Bagley, R. Aldrich, Robert W. Purcell.
- AIA - Brazil, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 0007A)
- AIA - Brazil, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 0007B)
- AIA - Brazil - Highway Construction, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Study of possible ways to finance highway construction. Plans tabled.
- AIA - Brazil - Iron Ore, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Study of possible IBEC investment in ore lands. Not completed.
- AIA - Brazil - Sulfite Project, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  IBEC study of pulp wood possibilities in Brazil. Not consummated.
- AIA - Central American Program, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Proposal for Central American work. No action. Correspondents include J. Maddox, NAR, WKIT.
- AIA - Consejo do Educacion Vacacional, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Reports on activities. Program canceled 1954. Correspondents include NAR.
- AIA - CIDEA (Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education) - Booklets, 1949-1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Preparation of comic book publications. Sample of work. Juancito Salud.
- AIA - CIDEA (Inter-American Council on Nutrition Education) - Report of CIDEA Activites, July 1, 1949-December 31, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- AIA - Coffee - Cumbuhy, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Possible coffee investments. Study of "flavor" elements in green and roasted coffee. Profit and non-profit implications. IRI (IBEC Research Institute) involvements. Coffee seed smuggling in Brazil. Primarily IBEC, IRI research work at fazenda Cambuhy in coffee growth. Griffing report on coffee production (1952). African coffee. Correspondents include NAR, Berent Friele, John French.
- AIA - Ecor Inc., 1950-1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  A non-profit group to study and improve basic economics and trading relationships of U.S., Europe, and Latin America. Organization and program. Minutes of meetings. Studies. Dissolved in 1961. Did no effective work. Correspondents include NAR, Stacy May.
- AIA - Ecor Inc. - Financial Statements, 1951-1960 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- AIA - Ecor Inc. - NAR Statement, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  NAR comments on purpose. Drafts.
- AIA - Ecor Inc. - Dr. R. Mattioli, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  NAR correspondence with Mattioli on goals of Ecor.
- AIA - Employees, 1947-1958 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Employee program. Hiring policies. Problems. Job descriptions. Correspondents include NAR, John Camp.
- AIA - Employees - Pension Plans, 1947-1958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Incentives. Discussions of fringe benefit plans for NAR corporation.
- AIA - Employees - Handy Associates, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- AIA - Ford Foundation, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  NAR appeal to Foundation for funds to finance AIA type programs outside Latin America. No results.
- AIA - Gates, T. S., Jr., 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Served on Treasurers Advisory committee of IBEC. Reports on investment policies. Correspondents include NAR, T. S. Gates, Jr.
- AIA - General Coffee Co. Inc., 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Budgets and Finance statements.
- AIA - Graham, William L., 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  He had a plan for selling the private enterprise system to the world. He made personal loans to small local businessmen. Wanted NAR help. IBEC subscribes $25,000. Comments on his methods in India. NAR gave stock in PEI back to Graham in 1958. Correspondents include NAR, William Graham, T.B. Keehan.
- AIA - Hanks, Bryan, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Plans for low cost housing. Correspondents include B. Hanks, NAR.
- AIA - Hood, H. P. Sons, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Exchange of ideas on milk market in Venezuela. Hood advice. Correspondents include NAR.
- AIA - India Project, T. B. Keehan, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Sending T.B. Keehan to India as consultant to the India Cooperative Unit. Reports of Indian progress Cultural exchange program. Difficulties in India. Correspondents include NAR, T.B. Keehan, Louise A. Boyer, Walter Crawford.
- AIA - India Project, T. B. Keehan, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- AIA - India Project, T. B. Keehan, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- AIA - India Project, T. B. Keehan, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- AIA - India Project, T. B. Keehan - Eisenhower Visit to India, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  Keehan reports and observations.
- AIA - India - Confidential Memoranda: Report on Cooperatives and the AIA Cooperative League Work in India, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  Keehan returns to U.S. Reports on work of AIA and Cooperative League in India.
- AIA - India - Vincent Cheechi Plan, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  Cheechi plan for aid in Europe through cooperative organizations.
- IBEN Co., 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 36)